Finding aid to the Daniel Aaron Papers CA.MS.00369
Smith College Archives
Daniel Aaron Papers
1939-1972
Smith College Archives
Aaron, Daniel
CA.MS.00369
1.25 linear feet (3 containers)
Contains news articles, faculty listings, correspondence, photographs, books, pamphlets and manuscripts documenting the life and work of Daniel Aaron during his professional life at Smith College.
Biographical / Historical
Daniel Aaron was born in Chicago in 1912. He graduated from the University of Michigan in 1933 and received his doctorate in 1943 from Harvard University. Aaron's first teaching position was at Harvard, where he lectured from 1936-1939 in the Department of English. In 1939, Aaron joined the Smith faculty. During his time at Smith, Aaron travelled as a visiting lecturer to the Guggenheim (1947), Bennington College (1950-51), the University of Helsinki (191951-52), Amherst College (1954-55), the University of Warsaw (1962-63), Columbia University (1960-61), and MIT (1965). In 1961, he was named Jordan Professor of English Language and Literature. His articles and books include Poland: A Self Interview (1964), Men of Good Hope (1951), and the critically acclaimed Writers on the Left (1961). In 1972-1983, he became the Director of Graduate Study in American Civilization at Harvard University where he was named the Victor S. Thomas Professor of English and American Literature. During this time, he founded the Library of America. In 2010, Aaron received the National Humanities Medal. At the time of writing, Aaron still works at Harvard University.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains various papers related to Daniel Aaron's professional life. This includes correspondence with other scholars, pamphlets related to various conferences he attended or speeches he gave worldwide, and photographs of these events. A large portion of the collection is dedicated to Professor Aaron's reception by the public and other scholars in the form of newspaper clippings reviewing his books and reporting on his speeches. The collection also contains many of Aaron's published works, from articles to books, as well as the manuscript versions of some of these texts.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Related Materials
Daniel Aaron additional papers, ca. 1921-2007. Harvard University.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown.
Speeches.; Letters.; Photographs.; manuscripts for publication; Poland -- Description and travel.; Aaron, Daniel; Smith College--Faculty.
- General, 1961-1963 (Box 656, Folder 1)
- News Articles, 1954-1966 (Box 656, Folder 2)
- Photographs, 1961-1969 (Box 656, Folder 3)
- Speeches, 1960-1967 (Box 656, Folder 4)
- Speeches-St Lawrence University, 1966 (Box 656, Folder 5)
- Appointments-Other Colleges, 1958-1972 (Box 656, Folder 6)
- Conferences, Seminars, etc., 1954-1967 (Box 656, Folder 7)
- Conferences, Seminars, etc. - Latin America, 1966 (Box 656, Folder 8)
- Conferences, Seminars, etc. - Venezuela, 1967 (Box 656, Folder 9)
- Conferences, Seminars, etc.-Salzburg, 1965 (Box 656, Folder 10)
- Lectures, 1956-1966 (Box 656, Folder 11)
- Publications, 1939-1970 (Box 657, Folder 1)
- Publications-Edward Bellamy, 1968 (Box 657, Folder 2)
- Publications-The United States: History of a Republic, 1967 (Box 657, Folder 3)
- Publications-Men of Good Hope, 1951 (Box 657, Folder 4)
- Publications-In Memory of Joseph Freeman, 1965 (Box 657, Folder 5)
- Publications-Men of Good Hope Manuscript, undated (Box 657, Folder 6)
- Publications-Poland: A Self Interview, 1964 (Box 657, Folder 7)
- Publications-The United States, 1967 (Box 657, Folder 8)
- Publications-Writers on the Left, undated (Box 657, Folder 9)
- Writers on the Left Reviews, 1961-1963 (Box 658, Folder 1)
- Writers on the Left Manuscript, undated (Box 658, Folder 2)